Finding Aid for Michael and Janice Neubecker papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael and Janice Neubecker papers 1996-2010, 1996-2004
Neubecker, Michael.
3.5 linear feet
2014052 Aa 2
Papers of Michael and Janis Neubecker, co-founders and past Presidents of Parents, Families, and Friends of Lesbians and Gays Downriver, Michigan (PFLAG Downriver). Michael Neubecker served as the PFLAG Great Lakes Regional Director and Vice-President/Regional Director Council Chair. Researchers will find records of PFLAG Downriver, materials of other PFLAG chapters and of the national PFLAG organization, and material related to Michael and Janice Neubecker PFLAG activities. Also subject files and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Michael Neubecker (donor no. 11071 ) in February 2014.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Janice Michael and Neubecker are Newport, Michigan residents. Michael Neubecker grew up Catholic in greater Detroit area and graduated from the Wayne State University.
In the 1980s, two of Neubeckers' gay family members and Janice's former teacher fell victims of hate crimes; another gay family member was physically assaulted. In 1991, their son William (Lee), at the time a freshman in college, was not able to join the Reserve Officers' Training Corps program at Eastern Michigan University because of the military's policy at the time of not accepting openly gay troops. Michael and Janice supported Lee in his public protest.
In 1995 the Neubeckers started coming to local Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG) meetings, the organization for parents, families, friends, and straight allies united with people who are lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender. They were inspired to join PFLAG-Detroit after hearing then-national president Mitzi Henderson speak at the 1995 Human Rights Campaign dinner event at the Fox Theatre. Only 6 months later, in 1996, Michael and Janice founded PFLAG Downriver. Michael and Janice scheduled the first monthly PFLAG Downriver meeting in their basement in June of 1996. In September of 1996 the meetings moved to the Southgate church location. A Steering Committee was formed to formalize the FLAG/Downriver chapter and prepare bylaws and affiliation papers. The chapter received their affiliation papers in October of 1996. They became a chartered chapter in the fall of 1997. Michael was the first PFLAG Downriver President and served for two years. Janice followed as President and has served several years followed by Maryan Mackie who served for two years, then Michael returned to his role as President again. He also was the chapter newsletter editor. PFLAG provided a venue for parents and family members of LGBT teenagers and adult children, enabling them to learn more about being a positive parent or family member of an LGBT person, find common ground with other parents and learn how to be there for the gay person in their life. The chapter took active part in state, regional, and national PFLAG campaigns and petitions, and local events.
In 1998, with support of the PFLAG Downriver Board, the Neubeckers started a Straight Spouses group dedicated to helping straight persons to understand and accept their LGBT spouses. The group became an outreach of the PFLAG Downriver chapter.
In April 2004 Michael Neubecker was elected to fill a midterm vacancy on the PFLAG's national Board of Directors, only six months after he was voted Director of PFLAG's Great Lakes Region (Indiana, Michigan, Ohio, and later Illinois). As Regional Director, Neubecker represented the concerns of local chapters in these three states to the national organization, communicated with chapters about national programs and goals, and acted as a facilitator between chapters to resolve any problems or disputes in the organization.
After a 2012 house fire, Neubeckers moved to Newport, Mich. PFLAG Downriver members continued to meet until January 2013 but were not able to find effective leadership to run the chapter, after which the PFLAG Downriver chapter disbanded. Members continue to attend other local PFLAG chapters meetings.
Neubecker's son Lee is married to David who changed his last name to Neubecker and together in 2009 they have adopted two children from the foster care system in the Chicago area. These children have been in their home since 2007 and are brother and sister. In February 2013 PFLAG National filed an amicus brief in support of the plaintiffs in the landmark Perry v. Hollingsworth case. The case challenged the constitutionality of the discriminatory "Proposition 8" legislation in California that eliminated the right for same-sex couples to marry. The brief shared the stories of PFLAG families and the very real impact that their lack of equal protection under the law has on their families. The Neubecker family story was among the stories presented to the Supreme Court.
Neubeckers personally lobbied their elected representative on their concerns for equality for the LGBT community. Michael Neubecker is member of Gay, Lesbian & Straight Education Network (GLSEN)/Detroit and PFLAG liaison, member of Triangle Foundation Board of Advisors, and American Friends Services Committee non-violent training and dialogues participant. Neubeckers are Human Rights Campaign Federal Club members and supporters. They are also active in the Reconciling Congregations Movement to remove barriers to LGBT persons in the United Methodist Church. Michael is the First United Methodist Church of Flat Rock--Reconciling member, lay speaker and choir member.
Among their numerous awards, the Neubeckers received the Pride Award for Community Service in 1997, the Spirit of Detroit Award in 1999, the Pride Partnership Award from the Triangle Foundation in 2000, the Lifetime Achievement Award from the Human Rights Campaign in 2001, and the 2002 Motor City Pride Award, among others.
Michael Neubecker is the author of the 1995 book "Out of the Closet Into Our Hearts," and is an occasional contributor to Between the Lines, a periodical published by Pride Source Media Group, LLC. based in Livonia, Mich. He has been a talk-radio guest on WXYT, WJR, and WMUZ in Detroit. Together Neubeckers have represented PFLAG on six cable programs in the Downriver area.
Michael Neubecker also performs as a stand-up comedian. His comedy is rooted in his family experience and his time spent working with PFLAG. A good chunk of his routine is about having an openly gay son, and his humorous message is intended primarily for parents of gay children.
The Michael and Janice Neubecker papers contain material about Neubeckers' activism, records of organizations in which they participated. Also included correspondence and background material on various subjects related to the LGBT community rights. The collection is organized into three series: Michael and Janice Neubecker Files; Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG), and Subject Files.
Subjects:
Gay teenagers--Michigan.; Gays--Michigan--Wayne County.; Lesbian teenagers--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan--Wayne County.; Neubecker, Janice.; Neubecker, Michael.; Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays.; Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays Downriver, Mich.; Parents of gays--Michigan.; Transsexuals--Michigan--Wayne County.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Michael and Janice Neubecker Files
  The Michael and Janice Neubecker Files series (1 linear foot) includes Michael and Janice's correspondence concerning gay rights activism, containing discussion about homosexuality, and thank you notes. The series includes research notes, examples of writing, information about and evaluations of workshops that Neubeckers attended or taught. Two folders containing newspaper clippings include collected articles on various subjects as well as articles written by and/or about Neubeckers. The latter include items about other Neubecker family members. The William "Lee" Neubecker folder contains correspondence and newspaper articles about Neubecker's son Lee harassment complaint against Eastern Michigan University, his marriage, and other material. The Straight Spouse Network folder mostly contains issues of the Straight Spouse Support Line newsletter for Southeast Michigan, 1998-1999. Miscellaneous material includes flyers announcing Michael Neubecker's standup comedy performances, among other material. Photographs include images from meetings and events, as well as family photos.
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1996-2004, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Neubecker, William "Lee" (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - Newspaper articles
    - By and about Neubeckers (Box 1)
    - Collected (Box 1)
  - Notebook (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Research and writing ideas (Box 1)
  - Straight Spouse Network (Box 1)
  - Workshops (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG)
  The Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG) series (1.4 linear feet) includes records of the PFLAG Downriver chapter, as well as records related to the Great Lakes Regional PFLAG, local Michigan chapters, and the national organization. The PFLAG Downriver chapter records are the most complete and include Administrative files --by-laws, Board of Directors and Steering Committee meetings, President's files, Treasurer's reports, and material related to the chapter formation, mainly documents filed with the State of Michigan and correspondence with PFLAG national-- also memoranda, information about meetings and events, and lists of library materials. Also included here is a set of the chapter's newsletter PFLAG Downriver (Detroit), September 1996 through November 2006. Also found here is an oversize banner of the PFLAG Downriver chapter.
  Records related to Michigan PFLAG chapters other than Downriver --mostly Ann Arbor and Detroit--annotated by-laws that served as example for the Downriver chapter by-laws, flyers advertising events, memoranda, and single issues of newsletters.
  Director's Files represent the largest portion of the Great Lakes Region material and include correspondence and memoranda, handwritten notes, training and publicity material. Also found here are the Regional Board of Directors directories and announcements and programs of select events.
  The PFLAG national material includes select annual reports, Board of Directors internal memoranda and Board's communications with chapter leaders, and collected printed pamphlets and newsletters. Also included here are materials from the 1997 PFLAG workshop Reflections on Homosexuality and Religion that was attended by the Neubeckers.
  - Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Detroit, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Downriver, Michigan
    - Administrative records
      - Articles of Association and By-Laws (Box 2)
      - Board of Directors files (Box 2)
      - Board of Directors meetings' agenda and minutes
        - 1996-1999 (Box 2)
        - 2000-2006 (Box 2)
      - Chapter formation (Box 2)
      - President's files
        - 1997 (Box 2)
        - 1998-1999 (Box 2)
        - 2000-2006 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - Steering Committee 1996 (Box 2)
      - Treasurer's reports (Box 2)
    - Banner, outsize (Box 4)
    - Events (Box 2)
    - Library (Box 2)
    - Meetings (Box 2)
    - Memoranda and statements (Box 2)
    - PFLAG Downriver (Detroit) newsletters, 1996-2006, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Region (Indiana, Michigan, Ohio)
    - Director's files
      - 1997-1998 undated (Box 2)
      - 2001-2010 (Box 2)
    - Directories (Box 2)
    - Events (Box 2)
  - Michigan (Box 3)
    (State Council, Michigan Circle, and local chapters)
  - National organization
    - Annual Reports, 1996/1997-1998/1999 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Conference programs (Box 3)
      (scattered)
    - Memoranda and statements 2000-2004 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets (collected) (Box 3)
    - Reflections on Homosexuality and Religion: PFLAG Leadership Training Institute (Box 3)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files series (1.1 linear feet) includes notes and memoranda, collected articles, pamphlets, flyers, newspaper clippings, and other material related to topics of interest and activism. Hate Crimes, Religion, and Safe Schools are among the most developed subjects in this series. Hate Crimes files include the Triangle Foundation's reports, correspondence, memoranda, petitions, and other anti-hate crimes campaign materials; collected pamphlets, and 1997 report and guide for communities by the Michigan Civil Rights Commission's Bias Crime Response Task Force. Among files dedicated to Religion is a folder with drafts of sermons written and delivered by Michael Neubecker; also included here collected material related to religious teachings and homosexuality, specifically the Catholic Church and "ex-gay" ministries; also collected materials of reconciling congregations. Material related to church and homosexuality also can be found in the Homophobia folder. The Safe Schools files contain reports and newspaper coverage of administrative discrimination and violence against gay students in Michigan, the State Board of Education debate on the subject, and PFLAG Safe Schools Campaign material. Also present in the series is a large file containing collected material of out-of-state gay rights and human rights organizations on various subjects.
  - Downriver, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Hate crimes
    - Bias Crime Response Task Force Final Report: a Guide for Communities, 1997 by Michigan Civil Rights Commission (Box 3)
    - Michigan Alliance Against Hate Crimes (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets (collected) (Box 3)
    - Triangle Foundation files (Box 3)
  - Homophobia (Box 3)
  - Human Rights Campaign (collected materials) (Box 3)
  - Other organizations (collected materials) (Box 3)
  - Religion
    - Catholic Church (Box 3)
    - Collected material, various (Box 3)
      (includes sheet music)
    - "Ex-Gay" ministries (Box 3)
    - Integrity Detroit (Box 3)
    - Islam (Box 3)
    - Sermons (Box 3)
      (by Michael Neubecker)
  - Safe Schools
    - Safe Schools Campaign, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Safe schools Michigan (Box 4)
  - Same sex marriage (Box 4)
  - Suicide (Box 4)
  - Transgender community (Box 4)
  - Warner, Robert L. (Box 4)
Related Collections
Bentley Historical Library houses manuscript records, printed materials, and contents of archived web sites of the following Michigan PFLAG chapters:
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Ann Arbor:
Records, 1982-1996
Printed newsletters, 1985-current
Web Archives, 2010- http://webarchives.cdlib.org/site/sw1n873m3r
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Detroit:
Records, 1986-1996
Printed newsletters, 1994-2010
Web Archives, 2010- http://webarchives.cdlib.org/site/sw1dr2pw53
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Lansing Area:
Records, 1972-1999. Finding aid to this collection is available online: http://www.hti.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead&idno=umich-bhl-00140